hello and welcome it's December 17th
2024 we're here with Josephine Pam and
colleagues discussing free energy
projective simulation there will be a
presentation followed by a discussion so
thank you to all the authors for joining
looking forward to it take it away thank
you
um hi and thanks for uh having us um
today I wanted to present the paper that
we have um recently made public on the
archive um you can have the the number
here which treats uh the free energy
projective simulation active in Fr with
interpretability and our goal there was
to combine um an existing framework for
agency called projective simulation with
the free energy principle and um active
where we have an agent that is able to
learn from its experience in the world
Gathering percepts and remembering um a
history of actions to learn a
representation of its
environment and um behave adaptively in
its environment by performing active
Insurance to determine its
behaviors um I want to I have structured
my presentation in three main points
first I want to um introduce projective
simulation to the community um then I
want to um introduce the formulation and
the aspects of active inference that I
have used in these Works especially the
the notation will be
important and then the main body of the
presentation will deal with the free
energy projective simulation how what
isly Ure how does it work um how do we
train it and then some numerical
analysis about it before I
conclude so first uh what is projective
simulation the goal of projective
simulation is to model intelligent
agents with a framework that is rooted
in embodied cognitive science so now
what I want to do is to look at the
keywords of this sentence and understand
what we mean uh behind those words
starting with um the notion of
intelligence for an agent where what we
really mean here is that um the agents
we consider are able to perceive the
environment with um to perceive their
environment and are able to influence
and change their environment by acting
on it and in doing so they are settling
matters uh in the environment in a
flexible
way and then the agent uh uh brought
definition for it or um its support
would be a system that has a memory as I
said I want my agent to be able to
remember its experience in the
environment and it's also able to
interact with this environment and that
leads us then to embody cognitive
science where instead of having the
agent learning from a set of predefined
roles that we as designers would give to
the agent such that it learns um high
order Concepts the agent has to learn
from the information it has gathered
from its interaction history with the
environment that is how it has perceived
the environment and the action it has
taken on this
environment and now I have spoken about
memory earlier and I want to make a
Precision um for this intelligence it
should also um the agent should also be
able to adapt to situations that it
hasn't experienced yet by comparing it
to its
existing
um moments in memory and to be able to
compare them see which element of its
past history are useful to adapt to
unprecedented
situations now I want to dive into the
way we are modeling the agent to
implement projecti
simulation the agent is engaged in in a
procet action loop with the environment
in that it has two types of subsystems a
sensor system is able to perceive uh
percepts and stimuli from the
environment and it's able to act on the
environment and change its state uh
through its
actuators and the key of projective
simulation the place where projective
simulation will um be important is the
memory of the agent that is decoupled
from its
physical uh interface with the
environment and that should allow the
agent to reflect such that he can
display some more um complex behaviors
um in the environment going Beyond
similar response uh
behaviors the idea here is that the
agent is able to
um simulate possible scenarios using its
memories in order to plan or
deliberate um for its next action so
this is already this diagram should
already be reminiscent of the free
energy principle and active inference in
general now projective simulation is a
specific process that runs on the memory
to
deliberate for this the memory is um
depicted as a a um Network that connects
different clips if you want a if an
event where um a movie a clip would be a
snippet of that of that movie just a few
seconds of it where the agent would
recall the sensations it has had the
percepts it has had during this um um
mini movie and the actions it has
taken then the agent um the different Li
are connected in a directed Network such
that the the different events are
connected with one another following the
experience of the
agent upon receiving a percept from the
environment on its sensor um system a
clip in the memory of the agent in the
epizoic and compositional memory of the
agent you will hear me saying ECM very
often so a clip is excited by a peret
from the
sensors and then the deliberation of the
agent will take place by hopping on
those edges to um go from one clip to
the next and simulate forward um the
possible events that can unravel from
this excitic
clip so the agent does a random work on
that Network until it reaches a specific
type of clip that will then decou from
the memory and this um
um yeah fictitious uh random work such
that an action comment will be sent to
the actuator and the action will
actually be implemented in the
environment so here I want to emphasize
two types of states that can happen um
the any state that is any clip that is
visited in the um memory is either a
remembered um clip um a remembered event
event from the past or something that
has been created that is
fictitious and all the surrounding
events so the percepts and the actions
are um real and um at the interface with
uh the
environment there are two specific type
of clips that I want to
emphasize um the clips that c with a
percepts from the um sensors or called
percept clip and the clips that decouple
from the memory towards the actuators or
the action
clips now um how do we train this memory
and how does the agent adapt and learn
something using this memory there are
two ways that this can happen either the
agent is um creating new clips in its
Network either because it has received a
new percept on its sensors or because it
has created new clips from existing
Clips in its
Network and another mechanism that is
more important for um the present work
is an update rule where each of the
edges in the network is weighted with
what we call an AG value that can
increase and decrease as the agent
interacts with the environment and in
particular at each time step um the pre
the updated
weight decreases compared to the
previous weight with a certain uh
forgetting
rate and it's brought back to its
initial value um with the same
rate and every time um an edge was
traversed uh to make a deliberation that
received the reward um it is reinforced
with a certain
reward and from those H value then we
can define a probability distribution
that the agent will used to um um sample
edges during its random walk to walk
from One Clip to the next and
deliberate this is um this is it for the
mechanics of uh projective simulation
and its
conceptual um meaning there were a few
applications already in the literature
for example it has been applied in
robotics and reinforcement learning
where um um a group in in book had a
robot learn new skills from um existing
skills by preparing new configuration of
the environment that would enable the
agent to extend its uh previous skills
um it has also be used to simulate
biological agent especially the
behaviors of honeybee um of honey bees
when they are trying to defend
themselves so it's a multi-agent
scenario um um where each of the
individual um agents are coordinating
their decisions to uh be
efficient and there have been a number
of um Evolutions that have been proposed
on this um a standard projective
simulation um multi exitation projective
simulation
proposes that the clips are truly
compositional and a nedge is not only
between two clips but rather between
groups of clips that would represent the
current
situation and there have been also a
quantization of uh projective simulation
um in this semal paper uh but also this
has already been implemented
experimentally on a small
problem so this brings me now to the
second second part of um this
presentation where I want to um give an
overview of the free energy principle
and active inference so that we are all
um agreeing on um what we mean by um our
notations and active inference
here so the claim of the free energy
principle uh is that any adaptive system
can be modeled as performing an
approximate form of Vasan
inference so let's do as we did for
projective simulation and look at
keywords here uh what do we mean by an
Adaptive system it means that we have a
system that that is able to persist in
its environment and to do so it has to
exhibit some form of flexible behavior
and it has to be able to act on its
environment so that it can change it if
needed
and the main keyword is patient
inference here which um um means that we
can describe an an agent as as building
an internal
model that it is using data from this
environment in order to update this
model and that the the update takes the
form of an
optimization and another keyword I want
to emphasize here is that it's modeled
as perform coming patient inference that
is it looks as if so here we want to
distinguish between the um internal
mechanics of an agent um learning from
um stimuli it receives from the
environment and its actions and um the
mathem mathematical description that we
can give of that agent as updating a
model in inovasion
way and hopefully these two will be
reconciled uh at some point in the
presentation first um to introduce um
active inference before we introduce
active inference I would like to
introduce perceptual inference which is
um describing the process in which the
agent is constructing its representation
of the environment using the
observations it receives from
it the environment can be described as
having um hidden States and the agent
acting on these hidden States will um
cause or in um yeah will result in a
change in that hidden State however um
the environment is not fully um
accessible to the agent it's only
partially observable so the agent would
not see this hidden States but instead
only a small part of them which show the
observations
and in order to understand the Dynamics
on those observations and being able to
predict those
observations the agent will construct a
world model in the form of a partially
observable M of decision problem a pndp
using what we call belief states where
here I use capital letters for the
random variable and lowercase letters
for the value that those random
variables can take and the idea of those
belief States here is that they mirror
the the role of the Hidden states such
that the agent can use them then to make
prediction about um its
observations so similar to I'm sorry
similar to um the actions in the
environment taking an action um will
also U result in a transition in the
belief States and those belief states
have to be connected to the
observations the transition between
belief state is usually qualified as a
transition function and the um
Association of belief states with
observations as uh the emission function
and those two functions can be modeled
as um probability
distributions um here the probability of
the next belief State given the current
belief state in its action and the
likelihood is uh the probability of an
observation given the current belief
state which means that then we obtain a
well model that factorizes nicely into
two functions um the likelihood on the
one hand and the transition function on
the other
hand now we have said that the agent
learns by performing basan inference
which means that we need to bring um
another component um to the table for
the agent to update its model and that
is distinguishing between a prior and a
posterior the prior is the previous
state of knowledge of the agent but it
believed was true for the transition
function uh before um updating its
model and the posterior is a
distribution function that is part of a
variational family and that can be
parameterized with here parameter fi and
this fi will then be tuned such that we
lend on a distribution here that enables
the agent to make better predictions in
the future using its current observation
and the way this parameter is tuned is
by minimizing a quantity called the
variation of free energy that then gives
its name to the free energy
principle the free energy um or
variational free energy to be precise um
has um the following form where I want
to First Look at the second term um this
term here is called the surprise and
that's um the surprise of the agent um
getting observation SC environment here
uh given it was currently in the belief
State BT and we are aaging this over the
variational um over the posterior such
that this term becomes minimal when the
current belief state is able to predict
the current
[Music]
observation this also means that the
best way to minimize this term is um to
forget everything we knew in the past
and to only update the variational um
distribution here such that it picks
only at the belief state that is able to
predict this observation and to prevent
that we add an energia term to the
variational free energy that is
um zero only when those two distribution
remain the same and that is that having
a new observation does not do anything
to um the model so this um motivates the
agent to remember uh is previous model
and to um make a sort compromise between
updating its model and um generalizing
also to its past observations
okay so in this whole scheme so far the
actions were externally given I didn't
say anything about how the actions are
actually um chosen in this whole model
and how they impact the ability of the
agent to predict its uh
observations and to
um include actions in this uh framework
active inference um gives us a recipe to
plan for actions and namely the agent
will try to choose actions that are
expected to minimize the surprise about
future observations in the long
run um to do to do that the agent is
endowed with a form of intrinsic
motivation that helps it that guides it
towards states of the environment that
are beneficial for it um for example
that are helpful in persisting in an
environment or in um um doing
homeostasis for
example the way this is modeled in this
whole framework is by giving another
distribution to the agent that we call
the preference
distribution um that is a probability
distribution over the future belief
States and the future
observations and as for a perceptual
inference now the optimal actions will
be those that minimize
a quantity derived from the free energy
which is the expected free energy so a
sort of estimation of the surprise about
future observations in the
future the form that this takes um is
often um qualified as a tradeoff between
an exploration and exploitation where
this first ter we are I just let me
remind you that we are trying to
minimize this expected free energy so
here we are trying to make this term as
negative as
possible and what this uh is is the
entropy of um the belief States given
the current world model so the agent we
select an action that um is the most um
that leads to the most uncertain
transition in the world model such that
the the this uncertainty is resolved by
taking the action so this is an
exploration term it um
Fosters um Discovery in the environment
it want to resolve
uncertainty whereas the second term um
is derve from the surprise calculated
from the preference distribution that I
introduced earlier and it is a utility
term because this term becomes
minimal when the surprise over the
preference distribution is minimal that
is when the the chances that we do not
fulfill our preferences um or as low as
possible and now from this um expected
free energy there are multiple ways that
one can choose and plan for actions a
very popular one is to do a research or
using monteo methods and the method we
want to use here is to define a policy
from this expected free energy by
feeding it into a soft Max function for
example and
um having a scaling parameter in front
of it that would be negative such that
we ensure that um actions with the
lowest um expected free energy are more
probable okay so this is the end for the
little summary for active inference and
now I want to move on onto um the model
we are proposing the free energy
projective simulation
um some key features of our model is
that um inheriting from active inference
the agent um is endowed with internal
motivations and also internal rewards in
the form of prediction accuracy that we
um model using um a concept we call
confidence which will become clear
shortly um it's also uh it counts uh
among the implementations of model based
based reinforcement learning using
projective
simulation and um it becomes a hybrid
model between um a form of associative
learning uh between different percepts
um conditioned on actions um that will
benefit from the reinforcements and the
rewards the agent got from its
predictions and the behavior of the
agent is completely independent of any
reinforcement um and is fully d with
active
inference and one of the main um
benefits also of using projective
simulation here is that the model the
agent learns and the update role it
learns with are interpretable as a
legacy from projective simulation
here okay so let's start with the
architecture of the agent where um we
are trying to um
gather all the ingredients um necessary
for the agent to learn a world model and
perform basan
inference so what we propose here is
um um the for the belief states to be
encoded in the memory of the agent
because we want them to be decoupled
from the environment just as um those um
belief states in the free energy
principle and um
in order to avoid um having to learn the
likelihood at the same time as learning
the transition function here we give um
this memory a specific graph structure
um inherited from the Clone structured
um hidden marov models that have been
first proposed in this paper here and
successfully
implemented uh in this paper here to
build cognitive maps and in another
following paper I think in
2023 um
for navigation tests in this
one um the way this works is that it
postulate that an observation is
actually only sort of the tip of the
iceberg of um the full random variable
the agent would need to be able to
understand completely and model
completely its environment and therefore
it gives each observation a clone that
as we train with acquire more more
meaning and it gives a uh this
likelihood
deterministic uh form such that each
clone uh is linked to a single
observation at a time that is the
probability is either one or zero in
this
case uh to each observation we give a
fixed uh number of
clones and um the edges that are
required to take
um to deliberate in uh the
memory um will be split into two sets um
one I mean here two sets or n sets one
for each action that the agent can
choose such that we can learn this um
prior and
posterior in particular here um the um
parameters that we can update are the
weights Associated to to each Edge in
this
ECM now we could clone clip any clip in
the ECM and we are going to call the
belief State an excited clone clip that
is where the agent is currently um uh
sitting in its
deliberation once the agent has excited
a clone clip in its
ECM uh this will Define um the belief
say the agent has to deliberate over
in order to um uh sample its action and
what we do here is um each belief set is
connected to all the actions and each
Edge is weighted with a corresponding
expected free energy and then these
um uh these expected free energies will
Define a probability distribution that
will be um that the agent was sampled um
from in order to determine which action
to implement in the environment and to
use to make
predictions using its memory and the
prediction will be the observation that
is linked to the current belief State
the agent believes it is
in now I want to introduce um the
concept of confidence in this model that
is crucial in order to update the one
model of the agent we call confidence um
the
um we use confidence to track the number
of correct
predictions um sampling an edge enabled
in the future that is if I sample this
Edge to start with at the end of a
trajectory I'm sorry at the end of a
trajectory it would count how many um
correct prediction it enabled in a
trajectory and what I call here a traj
iory is a sequence of consecutive
correct
predictions um for the
observations now I want to um move on in
the next slide to show you how it works
exactly going step by step um in an
interaction loop with the
environment
okay so the environment starts in a
certain hidden State and emits an
observation that the en that the agent
is able to um receive through its
sensors then following this one of the
Clones uh corresponding to that
observation will be excited in the ECM
here BT minus
4 and the agent uh will sample an action
from this state here A2 and predict the
next belief state um it believes will be
useful in order to make a prediction
about its observation in the future its
prediction is then S2 because that's the
observation that is linked to
it simultaneously this action is
implemented into the environment and a
transition occurs in the environment
that then emits a new observation that
is again received from the environment
and in this case it confirms um the um
prediction made by the environment and
therefore the confidence of the edge
that was just traversed um is set to
one because it enabled a single uh
prediction in the future for now now
every time the agent samples a new
action and implements it into the
environment the com the observations are
compared with the
predictions until the agent makes a
false a wrong
prediction so here the agent predicted
S2 instead of S4 and that's where the
trajectory ends and the the network the
weights in the in the
ECM will be updated following the PS
update rule uh so here you will Rec um
uh remember um the standard update rule
where uh we decrease what we believed
before going back to the initial State
um of the
distribution and here the reinforcement
happens proportionally to the confidence
of um an edge that is this um Edge will
receive three times the reward scale
because it enabled three correct
predictions in the
future now um I want to explain how um
we Define the policy and how we sample
um how we um Define the preferences
espicially
we have two
proposition the first one is um trying
to understand what happens if we give
the agent the objective of actually
trying to um minimize its prediction
error directly embedded in his
preference
distribution so to do this uh we used a
um we modeled the preference
distribution to be the marginal of the
world model here over its actions
and after a little bit feding this into
the expected free energy and a little
bit of reorganization of the terms what
one finds is that the um expected free
energy B is St to be the Information
Gain um about the next belief state from
taking action a in the
environment now you recognize very
quickly that this is problematic because
we are trying to minimize the
information about um the next belief
State and this is a well-known problem
um which is called the dark room problem
where the
agent uh posted in a in a dark room and
without any incentive to go outside of
it that is a preference for a state that
is not in the dark room would stay there
because it's fully
predictable however there is an easy way
out um using our
model uh where instead of minimizing
here the information again what we can
do is maximizing it by simply um um
making the scaling parameter here
positive and we will call an agent uh
that uses this preference distribution a
Wandering agent and then the um
magnitude of a Zeta will tell how greedy
an agent is for Information Gain it will
um a bit like in epsilon gitty
algorithms it will Define with which
probability the action is actually
targeting a regions of Information Gain
or of uncertainty to improve the world
model now this um the second um option
is more directed towards um encouraging
the agent towards completing a task in
that
environment
okay and to do this we we first took a
modeling
assumption that if we were to give a
task that is externally given to the
agent it can only be modeled at the
interface between the agent and the
environment that is on its observations
or its actions and here we decided to um
embed the Target in the environment into
the observations only and to call this
part of the preference distribution the
absolute
preferences and um the task of the agent
then is to be able to use its well model
to propagate these
preferences uh onto the belief State
such that it
um any state that can be useful in
reaching the Target in the
observations get a higher preference
overall to do this we Define two
quantities first um we
ask how useful is a belief state in
order how
easy is it for um from the current
belief state to reach the next belief
state so sort of cost of uh reaching an
action from the current belief State and
the second quantity that is useful is
how valuable is the current belief state
to um achieve uh the task in the
environment
looking at the um first quantity we
Define the
reachability um as the mar the
transition function marginalized over
action so for example imagine you are in
this state B2 here um here you have two
actions going to uh B2 for the darker
observation um compared to one with the
same probability for um those two states
so the reachability of State B2 dark
orange will be higher than B3 dark
orange for
example a second quantity is the value
of a Bel state which is connected to the
uh value of the to the preference um
over the observation it is connected
to we initialize the value with um the
this um exactly that actually the the
absolute preference of the state it is
connected to because we are using this
clone structure so this means that if S4
is our
Target then the preference for those
three states the value for those three
states will be um the highest and for
all the other states it will be the
lowest and now what we want is to
propagate this preference to the other
states in the ECM by using an iterate
algorithm over um a number of steps that
will Define a prediction Horizon for our
agent and either the a the belief State
um
stays um keeps the same value as before
so those States will never um have their
value decreasing um as the algorithm
progresses or um the um belief States
inherit from the value of the belief
States they can transition to um as
Define with this term here with the
reachability and the value so for
example those two states here being able
to transition to these here will inherit
their
value and now to define the L ahead
preference distribution we combine those
two quantities Define children of a
belief State as the states that uh can
be reached from the current belief
States and um combine this to uh Define
this look ahead preferences and from
there we're going to um fit this into
the expected F energy and Define a new
policy that hopefully guides the agents
towards the Target in the
environment
okay
yes so far um we have tackled only two
um problems that could get in the way of
an agent performing a task optimally we
have solved the first problem of um
trying to learn the best world model
possible to make good predictions about
observations the second one is being
able able to plan actions efficiently
for the future using the world model and
another problem that arises when we use
um FEPS
is the estimation of belief States um
and for this we propose to estimate them
in
superposition what this means is that
every time um at the beginning of an
interaction with the environment the
agent will receive an observation but
won't be able to distinguish between the
Clones to start with so it will build a
hypothesis that contains all um three
clone CL here connected to that
observation and each of those clones
would be a candidate belief
state from there U the agent will use a
rule to select its actions simulate its
transition for each of the candidate
belief State and propose a uh candidate
future belief State and while the action
is uh implemented in the environment the
agent will receive um uh an observation
from the environment and from there the
hypothesis hypothesis sorry uh will be
um
um uh reduced by eliminate eliminating
any belief state that does not that is
not compatible with the observation the
agent received from the
environment and um
continuing um this cycle of hypothesis
predictions and confirmation from the
environment the agent will slowly reduce
the size of its hypothesis to a single
belief state that the agent is not
certain it is
in
okay this then
um um solves the three main obstacles we
solve for an agent to P perform
optimally in an environment and now I
want to um show you how this actually
worked in practice and in the code in
some um environment that um we um use
for demonstration
purposes um the the environment of the
task we tried to simulate was a
navigation task in a partially
observable grid um the
agent um this grid imagine has food in
its upper right corner that let's say
has some smell uh that Prov Ates through
the grit so the the closer the agent is
to the food and the more intense the
smell is on escape from zero to three
the task of the agent would be to then
reach the food um in there but compared
to other application for example grid
World um the agent only has access to
the span intensity to orient itself in
the grd and determine its behavior and
never has access to the cause inates in
the grid for
example and what I want to show you
first is that even though uh the agent
does not see the coordinates it's able
to learn only from um its um percepts
and it's what I call embodied experience
that is um receiving percepts from the
environment and using its actions to
predict what I show here is a figure of
merits for the a status of learning for
the agents and I compared the two types
of preference distribution that I
introduced earlier the task oriented
agent first with the L ahead preferences
and the wandering agent here in reddish
colors and we see that it seems that at
the end of the training um given a fixed
number of episodes it seems that those
two model converge to the same length
for their trajectories is um just to um
remind you the number of consecutive
transitions uh that led to correct
predictions in the
environment it seems that at the end of
the training the optimal agents with
either preference distribution perform
the same uh with a slight Advantage
seems for task oriented agents that seem
to converge faster towards this um
optimal
status um and here there are two
maybe um interesting features too um if
um we set the scaling parameter to a
value that is too positive that is we
make the agent very greedy for
information the agent does not learn as
optimally as the other agent and in fact
it learns worse than an agent that would
just be given a uniform uh policy so
would be fully um Act completely at
random and this happens my explanation
for it is that the agent then trying to
seek transitions that um are the most
uncertain will never revisit the same
and therefore this won't be enough in
our scheme to reinforce the edges such
that they are no longer uncertain and
that they actually stick um so it would
be a subtle um balance between
forgetting and reinforcing that is
difficult to implement when the agent
becomes too greedy and the second
scenario is here one that we already
know when we set the scaling parameter
to plus three uh for a task oriented
agent we are now maximizing the expected
free energy and as we would have
expected the agent stays um does not
learn well in these cases because it
doesn't Target uncertainty and it's not
even trying to um fulfill preferences in
the environment
now a second point I want to make is
insisting on this look as if um in the
claim we made for the variation of free
for the free energy principle I'm sorry
uh what we have tra I'm sorry what we
have trained the agent on was only um
using the confidence to reinforce edges
and never did we do anything with the
variation of fre energy however it seems
that if we try
the variation of free energy it is
actually a good figure of Merit to
describe to describe the agent and its
learning and as you see here these are
um uh a average agents um and their
variational Fe energy and you see that
as before wandering agent and um task
oriented agent converge to a very small
value um at the end of the training that
the task oriented agent go a bit
faster and here and interesting features
uh if you look at the individual
trajectories here of the agents um you
will see a little steps in the learning
curves which if you actually open the
blackbox and look at what happens at
these different stages of learning for
the agents it's actually corresponding
to the agent adopting conventions in its
clones to properly contextualize its
clone clipse in um the grid here to
describe its observations and
um geographical location in the
grid the third claim um I want to make
is trying to understand this difference
between
um um the task oriented agents and the
wandering agents even though it seems
that when the agent is able to choose
its actions by minimizing the expected
free energy um that the desk oriented
agents learned learned better than the
wandering agents it seems that when we
compare their performance by and set
their policy to a uniform one that is
the agent no longer are able to seek
transitions of um maximum certainty it
seems that wandering agent equipped with
a bare estimate belief State estimation
mechanism are able to
perform in general a bit better or more
uniformly better than um the desk
oriented
agents and that if we use this uh belief
State estimation in superposition with a
candidate belief States in um a
hypothesis that we are progressively
eliminating that for both um um types of
training this will double the length of
the trajectories for the agent so it
seems to be rather efficient at least in
this
environment now I want to EMP emphas
I'll emphasize um this
um um slide here which relates to the
interpretability of the model the agent
is learning and what you see here is a
train model for an agent that we train
in the grid here um and the transition
functions for all the actions uh the
agent can perform in the grid and if you
look closely and try to understand how
um those transitions happen
you realize that actually each of the
Clones um in the world model that was
initially only Associated the only
information they had initially was um
the smell intensity that the agent could
um perceive in the grid um you find that
those took on some contextual meaning on
top of it that differentiates them and
that Maps them to a unique location on
the grid that in the end they are able
to represent um a geographical location
um and
yeah so in this sense it's fully
interpretable the the final model is
fully
interpretable and one final claim here
is that uh the policy that the agent
learned as a result of this look ahead
preferences um that I described earlier
is optimal and what you can see here is
um we've trained the agent to either
reach the target here um that is reach
the food or um escape the food here by
reaching the the lower um left corner
instead and so this has happened without
intermediate training which just changed
um the absolute preferenc so this is a
very flexible behavior and we've
compared the trained agent to a random
agent and we see that it's a very clear
nearly optimal Behavior and the the
restrictions on this optimality is not
due to the the policy itself that is
optim um optimal but rather to the
belief State estimation mechanism that
we are using and um that would require
one additional step uh to be able to
fully identify the single belief that
the agent is and therefore the agent
takes this additional action to
understand where it is in the grid
exactly um so that's the slight of head
you might find um in these plots but
otherwise fully flexible and optimal and
we expect that in a larger environment
with a similar structure we would become
optimal okay and this brings me to the
conclusion for um this presentation
where we have presented uh a model for
agency um that combines projective
simulation together with a free energy
um principle framework where we have
introduce the concept of confidence in
order to uh reinforce edges on the
memory uh that uh corresponds to
associative learning between percepts uh
using this reinforce uh this um
reinforcements and that allows the agent
uh to plan for its actions flexibly and
to discover
uh optimal policies using this look
ahead
preferences and I want to emphasize
again um the agent and its model are
interpretable both because we can trace
back the deliberation um path of the
agent on its memory and also because at
the the end product um the world model
at the end of the training is
interpretable we can map it onto hidden
states of the environment of or the way
we would um understand the grid and I
think a nice followup work or a nice
connections with we see with other
fields is that this model comes with
aspects that are um plausible from
cognitive science perspective namely
well active inference uh has been um
already connected to um uh in order to
endorse predictive coding and the beijan
brain hypothesis
the Clone structured um hidden Markov
models have been proposed as a way to U
model cognitive Maps um for um to
determine behaviors and in memory and in
particular here especially for
navigation tasks um it has been proposed
that the Clone Clips can play this a
similar role as the play cells in the
hippocampus and also the Luger head
preference scheme um that we
propose here is reminiscent of successor
representation that a few years ago was
also associated with um the role of
dopamine in um kind of
um um how should I say combining
model-free reasoning with modelbased
behavior such that um the U an agent or
biological agent can have optimal
behavior and flexible behavior in a
changing environment
yes and with this I thank you for your
attention and again for having us here
and feel free to ask any question that
comes to
mind awesome thank
you would any of the authors like
to just give any reflection or or share
a little bit
about the paper while people in the chat
are writing questions
or I can read some questions from live
chat okay first um is the code
available uh not yet but it would be
available soon um yes I'm working on it
okay from Leo Deion
wrote great work would it be possible to
make this using continuous inputs and
outputs we are also working on it
actually um so hopefully yes it might be
a bit harder um but hopefully yes in the
future which would be
harder it takes a little um change of
perspective on how we train the weights
and we're currently trained to model
exactly that actually um so
yes cool
okay reconfigurability trainer wrote How
would task
orientation limit outcome
expectations or maybe a little bit more
more generally there how do how do you
configure
task this is a navigation task but but
what how would for other kinds of task
cognitive task performance how would you
bring that into the structure of the
model okay so at the moment one of the
limitations that we have with the way we
modeled everything is that we can only
um encod the task as an observation a
Target observation in an environment so
it doesn't have to be imagine the agent
is able um to perceive I am hungry I am
full it could also be observation I am
full so it's not NE necessarily bound to
a navigation desk it can um go to any um
it can transfer to many other types of
tasks now for sure there is a limitation
and it was already visible in the grid
world that I couldn't tell the agent go
to the lower left corner directly I
could only reach one of the three cells
that had um um observation
zero and what I have in mind or what
could be possible is to um
give the agent a few rounds of
interaction with the environment and
combine this look ahead reference theme
with some reinforcements or some rewards
that the agent would get from the
environment um and then this way the
agent could be able to identify which
belief state is actually corresponding
which unique belief State um is
corresponding to um the successful state
in uh the environment on top of the
observation that corresponds to it
cool just on
the projective side like how do you
parameterize the topology and the the
lumping and the splitting of these
cloned
Clips since it seems like having an
appropriate granularity and transitions
amongst the these clips is sort of at
the heart of how effective the method
would be
yes so what I'm doing at the moment um
is helping the model I I'm giving as
many clones as um as
necessary um to um model the the the
hidden states in the environment that is
if I have um for
example it's coming yeah here um you see
that the maximum number of hidden states
that would send the same observation
these three so I give three clones um to
um the model for each
observation
the the way I initialize the ECM um is
um the at the at the beginning of the
training the ECM is fully connected so
I'm not saying anything about the
structure of the environment in the in
the ECM to start with except in the
number of clones that I'm giving and
then um we have been discussing also
techniques that could um have the agent
have an Adaptive
um way of defining the number of clips
for or number of clones for each
observation where um for example if the
agent realizes it needs more clones we
could add some and then add a specific
rule to connect them to the following
month and also what is also very nice is
if we give too many to start with and
then we are able to reduce to the
minimal amount of clones that would be
required to represent each observation
we could actually learn something called
a minimal representation of the
environment and that is something that
is very valuable from a theoretical
perspective as
well yeah uh do those clips directly
provide the interpretability or what
kinds of statements in a grid world or
just more generically what kinds of
interpretability EX questions can you
derive here that using some other kind
of Knowledge Graph or
graphical cognitive model couldn't
yield okay so I can only talk about um
the things that I know um so here what I
want to say is that um in general Clips
in projective simulation are understood
as a part of the experience of the agent
so by um uh construction at the
beginning they have a um semantics
Associated to them and here the the way
we follow this is by saying at the
beginning any clip is something in the
environment that emits the same
observation and in that sense it is it
has some
interpretability then this mapping that
we can do at the end of the training um
allows us to map um
the um clones onto actual hidden states
in the environment and in that sense
because we can kind of open the world
model and um take it apart and still
understand what's happening in that
sense it's interpretable and also one
way that this model is interpretable and
um compared to others is that at any
time the agent is able to deliberate we
can trace the deliberation path that the
agent is taking in its memory so we know
exactly why an agent is taking that
decision and not another one and that's
also how we reforce the model so we
understand how it went there how it came
to learn this model in um the first
place do any other authors want
to add any comments
ideas maybe I can just add you know or
try to to uh respond to your question in
what sense you know where is the
interpretability I mean these the clips
that Josephine was introducing and
talking about um these are internal
representations of actions the agent did
and uh perceptions it had so they the
semantics derives from the description
of you know its environment what it how
how it canect on an environment what it
can perceive from the environment this
is the the basic semantics there is and
it it inherits the semantics uh onto
this clip Network in its
ECM and so you know if what josephin
said you know if you want to understand
why did you do this action giving this
percept you can trace the sequence of
hoppings uh in these Elementary Clips
which are stored percepts and actions it
has done in the past so there's a basic
uh interpretability there how it came
about to to toh take a certain action
what considerations it went through as
it were now the clip um Network can grow
and change over time dynamically then it
gets more complicated when there new
clips are created how do you how do you
transfer the semantics to them as long
as you can trace how the clip creation
processes took place you can you can
connect the semantics of the new clips
to the previous Clips where it was made
from but then it gets more complicated
but the statement is that the basic PS
comes with a basic structure of
interpretability that is inherited from
the task environment which is often an
MD Mark
of decision process
thank you a
Marius um perhaps to that I might um add
a few
things um so first of all I think
there's some additional um
interpretability in the way the updates
are actually done um for example this
confidence mechanism and the update
rule perhaps the more obvious machine
learning approach to take here would be
to use the variational free
energy um a loss to do a gradient
descent on um but this can become quite
messy because there are all these um
different terms competing with each
other and it's not really so clear what
one actually gets from that and we now
on the other hand have this update rule
that very specifically says um that the
um probabilities are reinforced um
exactly dependent on the number of
predictions that they enabled during the
training and right now we are taking
here
and like in Parts it's a tabular
approach one could say and there is some
strength on it because in principle one
can write down everything as a matrix
and really inspect it um what's the best
transition to take what is the best
action to take and what is the best
state to
predict and um you know there are some
papers in the variation of free energy
literature and active influence
literature that directly throw
artificial new networks at everything
and as long as one wants performance
it's probably the most uh the best thing
to do but of course they come with all
the interpretability disadvantages So
currently we are looking on purpose on
environments and agents um that are
complex enough to be interesting and
difficult but small enough to en able a
manual inspection but in the context of
this project the idea is really to see
how does the agent evolve how does it
learn how do all all our principles that
we have variational free energy and PS
actually manifest itself what do they do
in the
Asian and for the um clone State
something that one like I think there
are some important intuitions that one
can give on those
um one can for example see the Clone
index as providing a context but one can
also think of it as dividing the um
decrease of Freedom into the observable
ones these go into the actual
observation and the unobservable ones
which go into the Clone
index yes like um so like here um we
actually see um in this figure here how
The Clone
indices um of the agent
um uh directly relate to the actual True
World model or the true states of the
environment so we can literally say okay
like this clone state is this
environment State and so on and we can
directly um investigate how the world
model of the agent actually relates to
the true environment model and if you
just used
um um like some artificial newal Network
you could not really draw a map like
this or C like
this
um if you don't mind I would as to have
some additional comments on questions
that were raised earlier yeah go for it
um so there was the question about the
applicability to um the con to
continuous domains
and one thing that's typically done in
NE symbolic um AI approaches for example
is to only use the um tabular methods um
essentially as one uh part of the
workflow um for example something that
one sees quite commonly in the new
symbolic AI literature is that one has
artificial newal networks that act as
feature extractors
and then the more symbolic methods get
applied to the um outputs of those
feature extractors which is something
that could be also applied here but as
Josephine already mentioned we um
working on an a generalization to The
Continuous domain that's much more
faithful to the methods that they
presented here
so yeah so I just want to um emphasize
that it is um possible to um generalize
this to the continuous domain and we are
actively working on it and we have very
a very specific Vision in how we want to
make it
happen so just to clarify this image
here the location of the grid like the
number of each cell or the X or Y
location is not being revealed to the
agent but they are being able to
perceive this ranked score like pherone
intensity or like temperature or
something like that and they're
learning through
their embodied activity the transitions
amongst that categorical
variable and it's sort of
recapitulating the actual spatial
distribution even though they aren't
coming to an explicit spatial
reconstruction exactly yes yes that's a
good summary of
it okay and so then that in the fullest
case there could be a clip
memorizing every single
location and then in the in
um in then a minimal representation
would start to Cluster coarse
grain repetitive
transitions
between like maybe if there was a
vertical border some of those could be
coar grains or just sort of simplified
because the same action would result in
the same
change yes um that's that's quite
correct actually if you look at some um
some observations actually only have two
hidden States so we would only need two
clones to represent those and what
happens is that since each clone is
related exactly to a single location in
the grid um the two clones are
representing exactly the same location
and we could design a rule such that
those two clones collapse and here those
three clones collapse and then we would
have
exactly uh the minimum number of clones
we would have in the in the ECM would
correspond exactly to the number of
hidden States we need to model in the
environment to be able to predict
observations
H okay I'll read another question from
the live chat and then if any other
authors have thoughts on anything okay
Leo
wrote How long did it take for it to
train to solve the grid task and how
scalable is this network with the amount
of beliefs and
actions
um I think uh it took a few hours for um
the navigation tasks um maybe the order
of four hours I think um so it's a
trade-off at the moment between keeping
the interpretability being able to
understand um everything that's
happening in the model and the kind of
the scale of the models we are
tackling um so this is work in progress
at the moment being able to scale up
this approach maybe we can um consider
that um
as um Marius was saying this featur
trctor could be helpful in um scanning
up to larger environments this idea of
um adaptive number of clones is also
interesting for this um
and yes maybe using a hierarchical
scheme could also be useful we don't
know yet but this is something that we
are actually thinking about and um that
we would like to try to handle but we
don't have a solution for it
yet what what kinds of settings have
these graphs absent the free energy
principle angle been applied
towards and would those be the kinds of
settings that then you'd adapt this
method towards or do you see this
as tackling a different set of
functions um when you say this kind of
graphs do you mean the Clone structured
graphs yeah
are okay so to my knowledge this has
been applied to navigation
tasks um there was another
paper I don't remember exactly what kind
of task that was the the more recent
paper where they learn schemes um using
this loan structured graph um I don't
remember which kind of tasks they used
it on um but I I do expect that they
transfer to most of the tasks what is
interesting is to have
some some ambiguity in the environment
some partially
observable environment um I think that's
where they're
interesting um yeah I am not fully
certain about the answer probably to
this maybe a degree of microbi also
might be necessary since we are only
modeling hopping from one step to the
next at the moment um yeah this is
something to to look
into yeah it's an
interesting challenge with wanting a
situation that's simple enough to
understand but not totally baked in so
that it's obvious and these kinds of
almost meta modeling considerations come
up all the time like if the agent
doesn't understand the efficacy of their
actions what are they even doing
inference on but if they entirely know
the efficacy of actions then it's Sol
then it's kind of like all loaded up for
them to know what to do and then how
many layers or what ways do you pull
back oh well it will learn the efficacy
of the action but that might also not be
realistic and so just figuring out what
expressivity of the modeling situation
do we even want to set up because
setting up what cognitive functions for
the to perform is kind of like just the
complement of the tasks that it was not
set up to perform and sometimes that can
be a bigger
component so I'm just curious I guess as
we sort of come to the end like your
broader lab and group what kinds of
questions and applications are you
seeking to bring these methods
towards and how do you see this work on
the path of of your broader
directions
um okay so for myself they are two
directions that I'm currently interested
in and I'm still at the beginning
of my career I would say so it's up to
Evolutions um I am interested in the
um ability of those models to um
coincide with actual cognitive processes
that happen
in biological agents to be able to model
that to maybe provide a tool that can
help us understand this kind of
deliberation and then to see how we can
um
um bring this understanding onto
artificial intelligence models and
matchine learning models in
general this is the first aspect I'm
interested in the second one would be um
how do we discover or or from these very
basic experience the agent has with the
world how do we discover how does such a
an agent build abstractions um and use
them in ways that are um efficient in
coping with the environment and
Performing
um yeah um fulfilling some preferences
in the environment I think that's so far
the two things I am
thinking about I think that projective
simulation has been used in uh on many
problems um as a reinforcement learning
methods on um you know it has been
benchmarked on those um um traditional
problems for um reinforcement learning
the mountain car problem grid World also
it works very well um also on some
um yes I guess modeling um is usually
the the main application does anybody
have other application in
mind bit yeah I can I can jump in oh H
do you wanna go ahead yeah I can jump in
a little bit um because I think one of
the things that really interests me and
and I know some of the other folks in
this group is um modeling in particular
animal behavior um and and foraging um
and so one of one of the big questions
that I think of driving some of this
work is uh how animals Forge for
resources that are sparsely but
predictably concentrated in space and
time and in particular when those when
those resources are depletable and
dynamic um and so this this poses a
problem where um one scheme is not
sufficient for the animal to come up
with foraging decisions so in this
framework we might see this graph that
we have up on the screen on the screen
as as one scheme that allows an agent to
solve a task and so this this work has
helped us to think about how the free
energy principle can be used to help
learn this scheme in a reinforcement
learning Paradigm through this process
of reinforcing deliberative Pathways um
but then what the projective simulation
model can do for us is start to help us
think about how an agent can build up
different schemes from a set of episodic
memories um and so I think that this
this work is kind of serving as a
foundation to help us move in that
direction of of how we can get use
projective simulation to get to a set of
schemes and think about a deliberative
pathway that's helping agents build
simple schemes of their current world um
from a more complex and Rich set of
memories that give them a full scheme of
the world um and and hopefully this can
help us to start modeling some of the
complex foraging tasks that animals face
um that may be um kind of the the the
filters system for natural selection
that has acted on the evolution of
intelligence and in humans and in other
animals cool thank you to to bring that
back to like what is the task that the
agent is set up to solve or not like in
Grid World foraging examples often the
location is given to the agent and then
the agent is doing like this navigation
as if it was doing GPS
and that is set up as the challenges and
trade-offs are derived from that setup
whereas using this projective
interpretability heris
scheme configuration it could just be
the learnt relationships between like
Shadow and light
or other kinds of sensory cues that
might be pretty coarse grains and so
it's not to say that there isn't an X
and A Y location it just that when
that's what's given to the agent or the
the ID of each cell number is given to
the agent then it's kind of like way
going down this road that animal
foraging may not even resemble and so
this can I think hopefully bring it to a
space of having the different
experiences or Clips like the honeybees
going on these orienting flights and
they go out and they come back before
they start to go for
foraging trips and bring back food and
so those kinds of her istics and and
then what curriculum would support those
Transitions and then each Edge can also
be seen as a node connecting to other
nodes so what should the structure of
that graph be and those are some very
flexible ways to talk about context
switching and all of
it yeah I think you're on the nose there
do any other authors want
to add any thoughts or what will they
work on next
year um I mean Hans wanted to say
something um because
um like of course uh so maybe um like
the answers given so far don't really
cover everything that we're doing in the
group yet um because most most of us
actually have um have a background in
Quantum computation so we are
physicists um who have mostly worked on
Quantum computation at some of the
points of our careers and um I don't
know uh Hans do you want to give like a
comprehensive Summary of why we care
about explainable Ai and um world model
building or should I no maybe I can just
uh uh you know say something I I think
Alexander gave a very nice Outlook and
also embedding of all this uh paper and
this Research into the into the foraging
and and behavioral
biology U projects that we are following
and I don't want to add much more to it
I see the still larger scope of this is
that for several years we have now been
really trying to understand agency and
how to to model
agency
um really in a in a in a physical in a
physical model so a notion of agency
that is you know uh accounts for certain
uh philosophical aspects as you know
planning having an intention and and uh
being situated in environment trying to
get around being adaptive flexible
things like this a non-computational
understanding of agency this is what we
want to model and this is another step
forward it connects to some branch that
we are also following in the group and
this is what what mariio hinted at and
and that has to do with the modeling of
artificial
agency to what extent can one uh
understand or even build artifacts that
can also learn but act in a meaningful
way on an environment have
a a certain notion of
memory that helps them to build model
and understand their environment yeah
and that's of course something in
physics and in the in the ongoing
development of AI and its use in science
is uh that is quite relevant so what we
want to understand is or to develop a
perspective on AI that one could call
artificial agency now in the future we
envision there will be devices that can
themselves learn and interact with with
an environment that do you know that
perform experiments people are now
speaking of self-driving Laboratories
and stuff like that and that is all
within a certain Paradigm and framework
that's being developed at the moment but
I think what we need to understand is
really to to which extent can one call
these or future artifacts agents to get
really a relation to what they do and
compared to what we do and how we are
and and that's the broader scope and of
course because to understand agency we
should also be able to model biological
agency yeah to have a clear to put what
we would call artificial agency into
context to what exists already that is
biological agency these are different
directions and dimensions of the of the
of the research We are following in but
that's I would say the bigger
picture thank you for adding that
anyone else want
to add any
comments the last piece just makes me
think about observing the animal in the
grid worlds and that's but you don't see
inside with the construction of
artificial or synthetic
agencies then it opens up kinds of
interpretability that aren't available
like to the bird watcher and so there's
some systems that were just watching the
bird and then there's other systems
where people are talking about designing
it and so being able to have a a
shared understanding and
formalisms that that
connect between those interpretability
settings and and even no there might be
things that are um interpretable from
the outside but not from the inside or
or at least even just the possibility of
those kinds of questions and
understanding where they always
sometimes never
happen
is important research on the path
towards this sort of more agentic Niche
that you're pointing towards
hunts awesome well thank you again for
the presentation and keep us Post on the
work and good
luck thank you for having us thank
you for